howdy this is Jim rut and this is the
Jim rut show
[Music]
listeners have asked us to provide
pointers some of the resources we talked
about on the show we now have links to
books and articles referenced in recent
podcasts that are available on our
website
we also offer full transcripts go to Jim
ruts show com
that's Jim ruts show com today's guest
is Eric Smith he's a researcher at the
earth Life Science Institute in Tokyo
and is in the biology department of
Georgia Tech he's also external faculty
at the Santa Fe Institute thanks Jim
it's great to be here it's great to
reconnect with you Eric you were one of
my favorite people from my time at SFI
when I was a full-time researcher at SFI
rather often if I just had a conundrum I
would go talk to Eric and it was amazing
no matter what the area was Eric could
provide some interesting insight Eric's
my background and training a statistical
physicist Caltech and then his PhD from
University of Texas but in fine SFI
fashion he's used those tools to invade
many other fields including at least
origins of life the nature and origins
of language money and finance as
institutions evolutionary game theory
and ecosystem sustainability is the
author of too deep and important books
the guidance of an enterprise economy
with martin shubik and the origin and
nature of life on earth the emergence of
the fourth geosphere with my good friend
recently departed harald Moritz
but Before we jump into these scientific
topics eric has also spent a
considerable amount of time over the
years in China and has recently
refreshed his knowledge of China with a
trip over there and he's got some
interesting perspectives on that whole
China thing so Eric what do you think of
China what do you think about it well
anybody who's been there will tell you
that the the pace of change is striking
from people who were born there to
outsiders and that certainly is right
the thing that's interesting is what's
changed and what hasn't changed of
course I mean China's not one thing a
country of 1.6 billion people is many
things to many in the business sector
you can see the concentration of wealth
and the confidence that it brings you
can see that China wants to be back in
what it
considers its natural place as kind of
the central front country in the world
and everything they're doing is aware of
the wish to get back there but there are
certain things from the old days that
have not changed my contacts are mostly
academics and there's a cheerfulness and
a sincerity and a sense of goodwill in
trying to address deep questions and
just a joy and community and a joy and
collaboration that's the same as it
always was and a friendliness and
cheerfulness and welcoming people there
so it's it's been a good reconnection
after a while away the nature of the
Chinese system is something I'm very
interested in it's not really exactly
like anything we've ever seen before do
you have any insights into the nature of
what we might call the Chinese social
operating system
well it's intriguing right the Chinese
idea of good governance since time and
memorial has been benevolent
dictatorship and that shapes a lot of
what they think can work on a lot of
what they think doesn't need to be tried
they see the innovations in the
manipulation of opinion that are
happening worldwide and I think they
don't trust civil society as a machine
to control that but they think that it
can be centrally controlled and this
whole engineering project is an attempt
to make that work it's interesting you
look at the history of China even though
obviously it has a very deep history in
time across a geographic space it's also
a classic case of punctuated equilibrium
where you know highly centralized
command and control systems work until
they don't and when they break down
they've often broken down very rapidly
you know this would be an interesting
experiment to see if with modern tools
they can make centralized control
actually being at least metastable yeah
this is the thing to ask the experts who
really spend a lot of time there and
know the society and the people in it
well because I think they will say that
there are combinations of centralized
control and an attempt at innovation
that have always been believed in the
past to be impossible and the question
is were they really impossible or was
that context dependent and I don't think
anybody knows yeah that's the that's the
question right and it is a competing
model there's no doubt about it you know
there's obviously hypotheses that china
is still benefitting very substantially
from
syndrome where they don't have to invent
nearly as much as say the West did so
they can rise rapidly basically
absorbing the technology and expertise
of the West and they've done it better
and faster than anybody I guess even
better than the Japanese but in some
areas they are really at or near the
state-of-the-art like an AI have you
gotten any exposure to what's going on
at AI in China no I'm a viewer of that
information like most people who are not
specialists in the area the interesting
thing about AI is whether it's gonna be
a classic example of Philip Anderson's
more is different so we understand for
instance from deep learning that the
ideas that are now dominating the field
were not created in recent time there
Carnegie Mellon computer science
department from the 1970s and 80s it's
just that those ideas were not viable
for the scale of computing in data
particularly training set data and the
ability to use it had reached the modern
level and China is going to be the
world's largest repository of integrated
data in the decades going forward the
question is whether there will be new
conceptual horizons that show up with
that increase in scale that we didn't
foresee Chinese certainly understand the
criticality of data at least with deep
learning though and people listen to
shown oh well I think deep learning is
immensely interesting I suspect at least
it is not the answer to artificial
general intelligence at least not the
sole answer but it is clear that the
Chinese are gonna wire up their society
to produce lots more data than say the
u.s. is able to do if only because they
have five times as many people you know
what I like on this though I think back
to the I guess it was deep mind or no it
was alphago competition with Lisa Dell
in the computer human contest for go
playing I really loved Lee's comment at
the end of it where he was saying that
of course those had been the most
difficult games he had had to play but
that he had never enjoyed playing go
more than in those games because before
he was the best in the world in a style
of play that was essentially established
and playing the machine it was opening
peds of play that no human would have
opened against him and
is giving him an insight into the game
that had not been available to him from
anyone before and apart from the superb
character that that demonstrates in the
man I think that's a good way to look at
human-computer interactions that we have
all of these big branching structures
and the question is when will
computational solutions open PES of play
that human conventions were not
exploring that's actually a perfect
transition to our first scientific topic
because that would obviously be relevant
here and that's origins of life you know
the transition from the abiotic world to
the biotic world how did you happen to
get interested in this field once you
provide a little framing for our
audience about what are the questions
about the origins of life
yeah very good I of course came out of
high energy physics and in a period
after I had left that field and was
looking for something to do I was
looking at phase transitions which was
sort of the big idea of the 20th century
in modern physics in some ways more
transmissible across the sciences even
than relativity or quantum mechanics
which were domain discoveries and I was
looking at dynamical phase transitions
and the sense in which sort of
tautologically their engines and thought
well this seems like a good way to
understand how biology works but biology
was not studied from that perspective so
it was really hard to get domain
information to get up to speed and solve
problems and when I came to the Santa Fe
Institute and met Harold Laura wits
I met kind of my perfect complement
because he had been working in topics
and biophysics and physiology for 40
years at the time and said I have all
these signatures of the biosphere that
looked to law like to have been accident
but I don't know what kind of laws
should be used to explain them and what
Harold had done was cut to the very
simple core of biology where there were
few enough boundary conditions and few
enough components that one could think
about trying to bring laws of
self-organization to bear on them and
that was the beginning of a wonderful
20-year collaboration that has continued
to be a foundation of my work to today
yep I've chatted with Harold quite a lot
about origin of life enough for my
simple mind at least they get its head
around a little bit you know the thing
he always told me about he had this
amazing picture on his walls he was what
I would describe as a metabolism first
person could you tell us what that means
yeah I can tell you what it means
without endorsing it in the classical
sense because in some sense by now these
things are tropes they're oversimplified
positions and in the oversimplified form
all of them are somewhat absurd but
metabolism first was in a sense a
response to a different absurd position
which you could call control first so
starting I guess in the 1950s Francis
Crick recognized that a lot of control
flow and modern biology is kind of
top-down you have the phenotype the the
kind of organism that lives or dies and
that life or death selection preserves
what genes are in the population then
through a very complicated control
machinery the genes are expressed in
proteins and RNAs and other components
which then make up the organism which
will have a phenotype in the next
generation so one approach to origin of
life was just to adopt Crick's central
dogma for control flow the idea that
control flows from DNA to RNA to
proteins and try to map that all the way
back to the beginning of life and if you
need to do that then you have to say who
are the genes what's the phenotype and
what are the Darwinian individuals that
can be selected and there is an attempt
to put all of this heavy burden on the
narrow shoulders of RNA molecules making
them the individuals that are both
genotype and phenotype and the thing is
chemically that's very hard to do
because RNA is complicated and it's not
clear what kind of a system it should
first appear in but also when you look
at the small molecule chemistry of life
it's a very low like it's very
economical and it's economical in ways
that would not be explained just by an
arbitrary control flow from RNA downward
so what the metabolism first point of
view was an attempt to do was to say
that a lot of those laws of deep small
molecule biochemistry were actually
inherited from regularities in
geochemistry the were there in place
before
biosphere formed and the biosphere
basically inherited those informed
itself around them so I would say the
modern version of metabolism first is an
idea that life is not one thing and its
emergence was not one event but rather
it's a kind of a hierarchy and a cascade
of events and in the event before you
have something recognizable as fully
integrated life you have increasingly
organized states of geochemistry and
they're organized around peds of least
resistance what we want in understanding
the origin of life is how those pads of
least resistance sort of set a template
for biochemistry and then that template
was strong enough and simple enough that
it allowed control structures like genes
and the central dogma to come into
existence subtitle of the book is the
emergence of the fourth geosphere could
you unpack that for us what were the
first three geo spheres and how is
biology the fourth geosphere so this is
the elegance of heralds insight on how
to break these problems down he was
quoting vladimir vysotsky
in the use of the term geo spheres and
it's a little bit of an antique usage
well a word geosphere is used today if
it's used at all it's not usually used
in their nuts key sense but when they're
nuts key first brought the term into
usage he was interested in trying to get
some traction over the great complexity
of geology and he said look if you have
a planet you can't ask what one molecule
does because one molecule goes all
around or one atom goes all around and
there are fluxes and currents and
exchanges so how are you going to make
sense of this big complicated system the
way you start is to realize that at the
very least you have three big central
systems you have the solid core of a
planet if it's an earth-like planet you
have a distinct subsystem which is it's
liquid ocean and then for most planets
you have an atmosphere and while each of
these is complicated in itself there are
certain things that tie them all
together the solid part of the planet is
solid state it's chemistry and it's
physics are those of solid materials the
ocean is liquid state it's chemistry is
the chemistry of what can happen
water which is permissive in some things
and restrictive in others and then the
atmosphere is gas phase and directly
coupled to the stellar irradiance and
the chemistry and the state of matter is
different in the atmosphere than it is
in the ocean or the solid so Vernadsky
referred to these as the atmosphere the
hydrosphere and the lithosphere nowadays
of course lithosphere is the top of a
rocky part of the solid part of planet
so the usage has changed in that way but
Harold's insight was to say that we
should view the biosphere the same way
we view any of the other geo spheres
it's a new state of matter it's
dynamically defined the rules in it are
different and distinctive from those of
the atmosphere or the hydrosphere or the
lithosphere and it is more tied together
by the integration of its processes then
the exchanges that it makes with any of
the other components of the planet so
how does the fourth geosphere emerge and
what is the mixture between the water
and the land and the air and as inputs
into this fourth gsv I know in talking
to Harold he wouldn't even rule out that
maybe life originated deep in a mile
below the Earth's surface in the rock
yeah the subsurface water alteration
zones are a very very good place to do
planetary chemistry and in fact since
life is driven by electron transfer
under sort of voltage differences it's
very difficult to find any other place
within the planet where you have so many
conditions that are good for providing
those electron transfer potentials and
also the catalytic environments to make
use of them so I think that idea is
still very much in play there's a quote
and I can't remember the source I should
he's a member of the astrobiology
community but it's pithy and elegant the
quote was that the origin of life is not
something that happens on a planet it's
something that happens to a planet and
that was really Harold's insight that
the origin of life should be understood
through the emergence of a biosphere
it's not something that's contained
within individuals it's rather a
transition of systems which means that
it's multi-component it's robust and it
changes the dynamics of everything
around it
so you can say that a biosphere came out
of chemical organization probably from
rock water interfaces in the chemistry
that they do the disequilibrium of the
atmosphere against the deep bulk of the
earth but as it formed it became its own
system with its own sort of robust
central tendencies and that's that's
what he means by the emergence of a
fourth geosphere from a planet that
formerly had had only three okay how
about your thoughts on how that happened
more to the specific but we have the
black smoker theories we have the deep
rock theories what are your insights
into sort of where and how it might have
happened yeah my first insight is that
we shouldn't try to spin scenarios at
this point when most people work on the
origin of life or have worked on it
traditionally they'll have really an
insight about one process that occurred
in one domain of chemistry at a
particular stage and that's the part
where they have a really good idea but
they say well how do i ground this idea
how do I know if it's a good idea
I should try to connect it to the things
that happened before and the things that
happened after and argue that the things
that happened before plausibly set up
the case I want to make and that its
outcome plausibly set up the things that
should have had them later problem is
they don't have good ideas about what
happened before and what happened later
and so they spin these long stories that
are mostly meaningless and a meaningless
story doesn't actually improve the
strength of the one place where they do
have deep insight so I think for the
origin of life we have to start a new
project that we've not known how to do
before which is how do we reason about
the good sense of a claim that's very
incomplete when that claim is going to
stay very incomplete for a long time so
this is a new problem in science in
processes that are very very complicated
and have a long history
all that said I do think there are some
general things that we can recognize a
planet like the earth is a battery all
of the materials from which it formed
the iron and the hydrogen of the early
stellar atmosphere those are very
electron donating materials but once you
separate into an atmosphere an ocean and
a rocky bulk the war tends to boil off
the top of the atmosphere and that's not
quite the right way to say it the right
way to say it is that the ultraviolet
and the x-ray from the Sun split the
water and the hydrogen escapes leaving
oxygen behind that drives the atmosphere
away from electrical equilibrium with
the deep bulk and you start to get an
electron transfer out of the bulk into
the atmosphere from which the electrons
are then transported off the top as we
lose our ocean to stellar breakdown so
there's a net electron flow in this
battery out of the deep bulk into the
atmosphere and then out into space if
you look at where that electron flow
occurs it dominantly occurs at the
spreading centers that are underneath
the ocean basins at this time this is
where new crust is being formed from
rock that came out of the bulk and was
not recently in contact with the
oxidizing atmosphere so I still think if
you want to look for the organization of
organic chemistry the places where new
crust is being formed or the best
candidates to look for that it's a
controlled chemistry it's a mild
chemistry it's not the violent chemistry
of ultraviolet or radiation and in being
mild and relatively low energy it looks
much closer to biochemistry than the
chemistry you would do with UV light the
important thing about Low Energy
chemistry is that if you don't have
catalysts nothing happens at all so if
we're looking for an origin of life of
rock water interfaces where new crust is
formed we really need to understand the
catalytic environment to be able to
predict anything at all now if you don't
mind that as a general context then you
could say are there organizing centers
in biology that look like the foundation
for everything if there were not we'd
have no story to tell but it
turns out that there are everything in
biochemistry that's formed comes through
a small system of only eleven organic
acids the biggest of them only has six
carbon atoms and this is called the
citric acid cycle on Earth today it
exists as a carbon fixation cycle but
even in the organisms don't use it to
fix carbon it still is the starting
point to synthesize everything so if you
were looking for a foundation for all of
biochemistry I think there's no better
evidence of a place to look than the
evidence in modern biology for the
citric acid cycle and it's really funny
if you want to ask is there one molecule
in all of this big planet is there one
molecule that is the center of
metabolism and the center of carbon
fixation its acetic acid its vinegar so
that is the central molecule for the
deepest part of the biosphere and a
thing's really fascinating is that I've
been looking more recently at the
organization in the amino acids sort of
continuing our interest in the genetic
code and you could say okay if acetic
acid is the core molecule for fixing
carbon and the start of biochemistry is
there a central molecule for the
beginning of everything complicated and
the answer to that looks like yes to
that central molecule is pyruvic acid so
biology is full of these little core
linchpins and in the way Harold and I
and others who are a similar mind looked
at the origin of life we look at these
as the circumstantial evidence for where
to to put the search light to do small
molecule chemistry that is really
interesting now when we talk about
catalytic cycles it brings to mind
another guest we had on the show earlier
Stu Kaufman and his auto catalytic
networks can you maybe compare your
ideas to his and how they're different
now they're similar yeah so there's a
truism that one has to start with if we
were just doing equilibrium physics you
can have organization that just sits
there you know a diamond will just sit
there for a very very long time because
it's a stable configuration under some
circumstances in metastable under
but if you're looking at dynamic
stability like we have in the biosphere
everything falls apart so the only kinds
of patterns that can persist are the
ones that continually renew themselves
now renewal can happen by a different
process than the process that led to the
patterns origin in the first place but
the simplest kind of renewal would be
one in which the mechanisms that
generated the process at the beginning
are those that continue to rebuild it as
we go now if you ask what this looks
like in material
well organization and material means
you're putting a lot of your material
into a few forms a few biomolecules a
few genes a few regulatory circuits
falling apart means that that material
drifts into the places that are not part
of the organization so you have to ask
what then moves material back into the
core of the organization
that's what Auto catalysis does auto
catalysis says we'll take things from a
general and diverse environment and
we'll concentrate them into a few
outputs but those outputs will be like a
kind of flypaper they're sticky for the
general environment and when the
environmental components stick to them
they get converted into the same
material that the flight paper is made
of
that's what Stu's insight is and that's
also what we recognize to be true so if
you look at biochemistry it's full of
auto catalytic cycles and those are the
things that allow biochemistry to remain
integrated and purified in an
environment where things are constantly
falling apart the difference between
Stu's approach and ours is the stew
starts from a very unstructured flat
kind of a combinatorial medium it can be
boolean networks it can be sort of
abstracted models for gene regulatory
networks and he wants the laws of large
numbers to give him feedbacks in those
large networks that can be a good thing
to do if you're looking at for instance
gene regulation if we look at
biochemistry the important thing about
biochemistry that's new in science is
that chemistry itself is a very
structured medium and we have never in
physics we have only understood
collective and cooperative effects and
phase transitions
in systems that have a lot of symmetry
when you get down into the dynamics of
chemistry you have systems that have a
lot of structure and the leading edge is
going to be to understand what
collective and cooperative effects look
like and how one searches for the
natural feedbacks and auto catalysis in
a highly structured system like organic
chemistry is so it actually has its own
structure one of the topics that comes
up in complex adaptive and emergent
systems is the fact that they're always
far from equilibrium as you said in
static physics diamond just sitting
there that's one thing but the systems
we're talking about need energy flowing
through them I know some of the SFI
people don't like his formalism but
Frigga genes idea of dissipative systems
for instance talked a little bit about
the energy fluxes and how they push the
system far from equilibrium and how that
is involved in the evolution from the
abiotic to the biotic route yeah very
good I don't want to downplay the
importance of energy flow because in
practical problems it often is the thing
that determines but I don't want to
overplay the importance of energy flow
because it's only incidental and the
fact that we're talking about material
systems that gives energy such a large
role if we really open our minds and
look at the statistics of
self-organization in the big picture
energy becomes only one of the flows
that can become important and there may
be other things that are not the flows
of something that are important so just
put a flag on that that we can talk
about the particular but we want to keep
our minds open that the concept is more
general so in thermodynamics energy is
one of the quantities that tells you how
much of your state space is available to
you other quantities are what are you
made of how much of each chemical do you
have how much of each element but also
volume are you partitioned how much
space can you take up so in equilibrium
the internal energy you have in your
system is essentially set the volume you
have your material composition is set so
the part of your state space you can
explore is fixed as you go away from
equilibrium you can couple one system to
boundary conditions that would not be an
equilibrium
with each other which allows energy to
then flow in through one boundary and
flow out through another if we're
talking about the origin of life you can
have energy flow in in the form of one
molecule and flow out in the form of
some other molecule energy flow in the
pre gaussian sense remains important
because the more information you provide
about the boundary conditions the less
freedom your system has to explore
another way to say that is that the more
ordered the system can be so a driven
system always has more information in
the boundary conditions than one that's
not driven because if I'm at equilibrium
all of my energetic boundaries have to
be in equilibrium with each other I can
go away from equilibrium in many ways
it's kind of like Tolstoy all
equilibrium systems are more or less
alike every disequilibrium system is
disequilibrium in its own fashion I like
that I can move the energetic boundary
conditions out of equilibrium with each
other in a lot of ways I can put energy
and in different molecules I can take it
out in different molecules I can have
temperature gradients once I do that the
restriction on the system's freedom can
take many more forms than the
restrictions I had available in
equilibrium and this is what Harold
meant when he said the flow of energy
through a system tends to organize the
system now the interesting thing is I
would say Prigogine does not go far
enough from equilibrium because if you
look at the work that he's doing in the
work that has continued in the hands of
many very fine workers who followed him
they still want the equilibrium state
variables to be the main thing that
gives order to the system so they want
pressure and temperature and chemical
potentials in the bath to re equal a
break quickly so that then they can
study the information in a system that
moves slowly and episodically in that
fast equilibrating bath but when you can
do something even more radical than that
which is that we can ask what is the
native thermodynamics of any stochastic
process driven in any way at all then
you contain the Prigogine class as a
subsystem but you can also go much more
general you can go into what I would
call the thermodynamics
of rule-based systems the beautiful
things that Walter Fontana and his
collaborators work on for systems
biology or the theory of chemical
reaction networks regarded as systems in
their own right rather than just
expressions of the surrounding physics
so I agree but I want us to be more
radical and more exploratory even than
precocious generation could be excellent
even stronger perspective you said
earlier that this origin of life work is
interesting and kind of different in
that we only know a little and the box
is big could you relatively briefly say
what you know or what you think you know
about what's inside the box yeah great
great it's a bunch of little islands
where we have repositories of
information and about those we can hope
to say a lot and then there are these
big areas where you don't even hear good
ideas being floated so I mentioned a
core biochemistry the carbon fixation
pathways the chemistry surrounding the
citric acid cycle the reactions that
tend to get used and how they're used we
have lots of recorded information there
and probably it's not even recorded
probably this is actually an extension
of the periodic table that is being
expressed by the rigidity of our
biosphere you go up a level and look at
the ribosome and all of a sudden you
have an extraordinary repository of
history about RNA and early peptides and
the emergence of translation and we
don't know what process that history
froze into place and yet we know an
amazing amount about what it froze into
place so we've been given the answer to
a final exam but we don't know what the
questions on that exam were that's
another place where we have a streetlamp
giving us tremendous light a place where
these two intersect is the genetic code
traditionally the genetic code has been
viewed as a problem of assignment or
shuffling where people take the amino
acids as somehow given and they take RNA
and the translation system is somehow
given and then they look for how many
ways you could assign amino acids to
codons in the translation system I think
that's a wrong view I think it's not
nearly dynamic enough because I don't
think the amino acids were given I think
the process of becoming biotic
was integrated with the process of
becoming energetically active and
discovering how to fold and I think that
when we understand the origin of the
translation system in the genetic code
we're gonna realize the regularities of
deep biochemistry fundamental physical
regularities of the problem of folding
and how easy or hard that problem was
different for peptides and for RNA kind
of bootstrapped themselves up and what
we see recorded in the genetic code is
the way each system got as far as it
could and then hit a wall and a
discovery in one of the other systems
that right now looks like it's a
different system opened a door for the
next innovations and they jointly went
through that door so I think we have
these little islands that have
information but we're our own
disciplinary boundaries have kept us
from seeing what that information is
about interesting now this comes right
next to one of my favorite topics one of
the topics we talk a lot about on the
show is the Fermi paradox like all good
fourteen-year-old nerds I said oh yeah
gotta be a hundred thousand intelligent
species in the galaxy well there's one
possible pruning rule and kind of herald
sense that I wonder about and this is
something I had like a six-hour
conversation with Stu Kaufman about and
we both walked away saying and that's
the following my home field is
evolutionary computation and one of the
things we know about evolution is if the
information fidelity between generations
isn't above X depending on the nature of
the system we have what's called the
error catastrophe where the ability for
evolution to produce very much is not
very strong and we have at the core of
the genetic code DNA not just a highly
complex structure but most importantly a
rather complicated machinery of error
correction and the two together give us
a high fidelity information substrate
for evolution that's well above the era
catastrophe and allows evolution to
produce things like ribosomes or maybe
they Co evolve but how one can imagine
chemical evolution
prior to this high fidelity
the information transfer system existing
have pumping up through evolution high
enough to created machinery of this
level complexity is white perplexing
does your work have any thoughts at all
about this problem yeah this is one of
those places where you stand on the
shoulders of giants and you inherit
insights that are very good from many
sources my mind's been out of this space
for a little bit so it's gonna take me a
minute to to get my sources back in line
a really great early thinker on this was
herb Simon one of the early systems
thinkers across fields and Simon has a
set of classic arguments about the
architecture of complex systems where he
says kind of like politics all error
correction is local and that's not an
incidental actually this is true for any
distributed system and this is where
decentralized banking came from in
England if you have a complex control
problem the higher order systems that
are your controllers are often made by
assembling building blocks at a smaller
scale but that means that they're
coarser and the information bandwidth
through the interfaces is too small to
keep up with all the things that can go
wrong internally to the building blocks
so herb Simon used to argue that if you
see a complex system in the world the
only plausible mechanism to have created
that system is one that has integral
error correction in the subsystems along
the way that creates sort of stable
intermediate states of assembly which
then provide platforms to explore from
for later assembly so herb Simon uses
the analogy of watch assembly you don't
put a thousand pieces in a watch
together holding them all in place and
then put a screw on the top instead you
assemble components of ten put each on
the shelf you put ten of those together
to make assemblies of 100 put them on
the shelf put ten of those together and
that's your assembled watch if you were
never interrupted it wouldn't matter
that you do those things but in a world
where you really are interrupted it does
matter and he used also the example of
the Alexandrian Empire where Alexander's
Empire was only possible in a relatively
sophisticated state system where
States could be left to manage their own
internal affairs so in looking at the
origin of life we are looking for where
in chemistry the pads of least
resistance tend to regress toward their
own central tendencies so that your
control systems don't have to constantly
hurt them back in those directions the
control systems can provide low
bandwidth signals to sort of make the
major switches between the stable or
metastable domains of attraction so do
we have any ideas about what was on the
pre side of DNA and its error correction
architecture yes
let me give only one example that one
could go on for a long time think about
protein catalysis catalysis by proteins
is obtained by first making a fold
architecture and then putting the side
chains of a bunch of amino acids in very
particular configuration that's a hard
thing to do because you don't get
catalysis until you have a lot of
supporting machinery so if you want to
understand how you could ever have had
the catalysis the proteins enable you
would first say is there any catalysis
by small molecules that's doing much of
the job within a small assembly that
doesn't require this sequence
coordination to happen and the
fascinating thing is that if you look at
the reactions that involve RNA and DNA
they often involve what's called
substrate assisted catalysis and what
that means from the technical side is
that the RNA molecule or the DNA
molecule itself is defining most of the
catalytic contexts and the surrounding
catalysts only needs to kind of orient
the components it doesn't usually need
to have its fingers in the transition
state of the reaction which means that a
much simpler surrounding environment can
be catalytic for those kinds of
reactions it's fascinating that RNA and
DNA would be the place where those
substrate assistant catalytic processes
are most common because those are
exactly the sorts of chemistry that
would need to have been in place to
enable the memory systems to get more
complicated protein catalysis very good
what do you see as right on the frontier
that we need to learn next in the origin
of
like we need to learn how to explore
chemistry did you unpack that a little
bit yeah chemistry is a combinatorial
system that is so big that we don't know
most of what's in it we don't know what
happens we don't have a system for
searching systematically and as a
consequence we don't have the ability to
reason about it the way we reason about
any mature science which is we you know
in most mature Sciences we start with a
hypothesis we get up to a point where we
get stuck and then we have the ability
to figure out what we don't know and to
backtrack to the last place where we
needed something and take a different
path in spaces that are so big we don't
know how to search them what we do
instead is we sort of ad-hoc based on
the expertise that any given person or
community has we explore some region and
then if it doesn't have what we want we
just kind of go back to exploring so
we're taking pot shots and this is not
to denigrate denigrate people's
expertise the expertise of chemists is
everything we have to go from and it's
extraordinary what they know and how
they can reason but the space of
everything dynamical that can happen in
chemistry is so much bigger than
anything we have understood before in
science that it just requires new
methods that have not existed before it
need to be created is there anything in
the emerging deep learning machine
learning space that looks like it might
be applicable there is work in that area
I'm not involved in it I know there's
some work being done by German chemists
the discovery of Hamiltonians there's
work from our wonderful colleagues at
the University of Southern Denmark and
the University of Vienna doing what they
call halfway detection I think this is
given a set of generating rules and a
set of inputs and products you would
like can you discover a pathway that
will get you to those products with the
generating rules from the inputs you
have and then can you optimize that
pathway by one or another criterion all
right well thank you Eric for that
amazing deep dive into the origin of
life will keep our antennae up for what
comes next let's move on to our next
topic is amazing there has deep work in
all these areas money
in finance and institutions my own
interest is most strongly in monetary
system so you know if you want to tell
the story from that perspective first
that would be fine but why don't you
start off by giving a general framing
about what you were trying to get at in
your work in money and finance yes so
this was very much a merger of two minds
and the leader on this was certainly
martin shubik whose interest for his
entire career had been the institutional
foundations of money and the nature of
money the role of money within the
polity and within the society so Martin
was a Rand era game theorist and he was
an operations Research guy which means
he didn't pursue the economic view of
institutions as at the phenomenal if you
look at neoclassical economics it's very
strongly rooted in preferences and sort
of the idea of the decentralized actor
and in much of the foundations of that
theory institutions don't really need to
exist they're sort of external
expressions of the preferences people
have and what you really care about is
people's ability to optimize their
preferences against the conflicting
preferences of other people in some
convex possibility set Martin looked at
that and said that doesn't make any
sense at all in the world I actually
live in the institutions of the world I
live in determine what I can know they
determine what I have the agency to do
they determine what communication I have
against every other actor sometimes I
don't even act against other individuals
who are peers I act entirely against
institutions such as the government
which is a coalitional structure and so
the institutions are the entirely the
conduits for what's possible so if we
want to understand the nature of money
or in fact the nature of most of our
institutionalized interaction with each
other we need to understand the
mechanisms that are possible for
institutions and also the historical
processes by which there arrived at
which can lead to lock-in so Martin's
interest was money seems like such a
sort of a primitive concept and a thing
that's at the center of there
everything we do how can we understand
why such a primitive concept can come
out of all the complexity of the
institutional foundations of our
interaction and I kind of joined into
that thread because that's very
congenial to my sort of physics and
mechanical approach to the world so we
would look at things like problems of
bank runs or problems of self-fulfilling
prophecies or self violating prophecies
from a mechanical nature how do the
permissions and the limitations and
institutions enable people or limit
people in the collective States they can
achieve good introduction let's start
with I actually did read long ago
Martin's the theory of money and
financial institutions which is a three
fat volumes and it's very interestingly
structured from the very simple to the
very complex by a whole series of steps
and so I'm familiar with that general
approach what could you say about what
you have put in this book about the
early stages pre institutional society
and what were those pre institutions
that may have given rise to the
institutions that did arise I don't know
how much you could say we did it was pre
institutional in some ways Martin viewed
our book as kind of volume four of the
the theory of money and financial
institutions which was meant to get at
the domain of dynamics this was the
place where maybe my presence was felt
in terms that will be familiar from our
conversation about origin of life the
origin of life problem was largely the
question if you've understood a lot
about organization in equilibrium what
do you have to learn that's conceptually
new about organization away from
equilibrium Martin wanted to ask the
same kinds of questions in economics he
wanted to say if you've understood a lot
about the stable functioning of
institutions what do you need to learn
that's new about dynamics when you're
trying to deal with transients or
adaptations to changing environments or
the origin of institutions themselves
one of Martin's favorite rants was about
how people had refused to understand
Keynes until they were able to miss
understand him so there's this famous
passage from Keynes
about how economists set themselves too
easy too useless a task if they only
tell us that after the storm has passed
the sea is flat again this long-run is a
misleading guide to current affairs in
the long run were all dead so Martin
felt that economists had missed Keynes's
main point that it's all in the dynamics
until Hicks came along and reformulated
Keynes in what's called islm which is
framing Keynes in terms of equilibrium
of investment in savings and Martin felt
that that had annihilated the whole
spirit of Keynes's point what he wanted
us to do with what he called him
strategic market games was to re-instill
the dynamical spirit of Keynes if you
have a system that doesn't have
stationary structure how does a game
create the solutions that are available
to you
perfect give an example a real-world
example if you have one sure so the hon
paradox for the value of money if we
only use money and trade which is
certainly the case to a good
approximation for fiat money but to some
extent it's a decent approximation even
for gold most people don't have direct
use for gold but gold is a store of
value and it's a medium of exchange what
determines the exchange price of gold
against things you actually need like
food and cows and houses and shoes and
stuff like that that number should be
arbitrary if gold is infinitely durable
and there's never a time when it said
nothing anchors that arbitrariness now
if you have consumption value for gold
but it's in the far future so maybe you
can use it for jewelry but that's kind
of a luxury maybe you can use it to pay
taxes but that's a long horizon then you
can say that that consumption value will
anchor the exchange value of gold but
now we have a problem in the order in
which we take infinities if I take the
future infinitely far off then it seems
that the value of gold should become
arbitrary if I take the future close in
then you're placing too much of a
regulatory role on things like the
payment of taxes and fiat money
so then the question was how do we
understand the actual fluctuations in
the trade value of things like fiat
money or durables in the in the real
world where we live my contribution to
that topic was that in the real world
fluctuations have a way of creating
stabilizing effects because they put
temporary uncertainties into the system
where they bring actors into the system
who would not be there if the sea were
always flat and so in fact the right way
to look at the long run is that in the
long run it's not the policing by very
weak regulations that stabilize you it's
the fact that the spectrum of
fluctuations and the set of
uncertainties that they introduce become
the stabilizing force that take over
from very weak policing actions in the
long run and one of the chapters in our
book is a model of the Han paradox
that's along those lines so to try to
chip in that it's a little bit is that
essentially saying that we need
uncertainty to keep the game going and
if the game became too transparent it
would stop working I guess that's
possible if you don't mind let me give
you an analogy that captures the math
it's not obviously about money but it
comes from evolutionary game theory and
I should tell you there's a third book
in addition to the two you mentioned
which is called symmetry and collective
fluctuations in evolutionary games that
was written with my co-author Supriya
Krishnamoorthy well now I missed that
one goddamnit but I'm gonna have to
order it it's an institute of physics
book it's sort of library only which
means it's too expensive they know who's
never gonna sell on the popular market
but we were interested in things like
what stabilizes the prisoner's dilemma
one of these famous games where you can
always cooperate or you can always
defect or you can be a conditional
cooperate or like a tit for tat type
player and in the traditional
formulations of the prisoner's dilemma
the conditional cooperator in an
environment of full-time co-operators
becomes invisible there's nothing to
protect his self protecting strategy
because everybody's nice all the time so
you don't have a way to anchor the
composition of a society between the
always nice and the conditionally nice
if you put fluctuations into that so
that occasionally some nasty guys come
into the system their presence will
distinguish the conditionally nice from
the always nice and they'll keep enough
conditionally nice people in the
population to stabilize it against
unraveling to the invasion of defectors
but when you formulate this problem
correctly in its fully dynamical sense
you find that the things that stabilize
the system are not anything like near
equilibrium fluctuations they look
almost more like solar flares they're
these big loops of excursion through the
interior dynamics of the system so
there's a new kind of a dynamical
stabilization that you need to explain
how a population has a non arbitrary
stable long-term configuration of the
always nice and the conditionally nice
who protect it yeah so we call that at
least in evolutionary computation the
search for evolutionary stable
strategies in this case it's an ensemble
approach right so that the society can
be resistant to predators by not being
too nice all the time exactly and this
is sort of the dynamically maintained
composition that is stable so it's one
step beyond Maynard Smith's original
idea of the evolutionary stable strategy
as a quasi-static thing in terms of the
emergence of monetary systems so what
degree are they endogenous are the eggs
honest they some combination of both are
they frozen accidents are they manifest
destiny of teleology where do our
monetary systems come from yeah this is
great
and this is a dimension where I think I
can add something that Martin and I
never discussed in our work together and
yet it would be the most natural topic
in the world and I think he would agree
with this point of view coming back to
origin of life and turb Simon once you
arrive at something complicated you
should ask how you got there through
pads of least resistance and things that
were simpler and if you have something
complicated like a governmentally
mediated fiat money that has a heavy
scaffolding of institutional supports
and also social norms to
get possible and Martin was of course
very interested in the role of commodity
monies barley salt gold and I think he
has a book by that title barley gold and
Fiat with Tom Quint he was very
interested in the role of these things
that have high use value in the short
term and they're only semi durable as
the entries to money systems the thing
that I think we could add to Martin's
body of work that's almost more
biological is how do commodity money
support the emergence of complex
institutions which then make more
complex money systems possible part of
this was in Martin's work and was
integral since before I was born you
know gold as a commodity money brings in
the problem of cheating and dilution of
the gold and that brought in the
printing of coins and the idea of
defacement when the Kings faces on the
coin and if you scrape gold off the face
in order to try to steal some of it the
king can kill you for this which is
where defacement of coinage came from so
now a functioning monetary system can
increase the strength of the central
state and its ability to enforce laws
but once the central state is stronger
then you can start to have base metals
like aluminum which are the foundation
for coinage that don't have intrinsic
value and are supported entirely by the
punishment against defacement so that
bootstrapping between the easier forms
of money but the less flexible forms and
the support of more complex institutions
that give money systems more flexibility
there's still more work to do in that
beyond even the considerable work that
Martin already did you may know I've
done a fair amount of work on monetary
systems and in my demonology I focus a
lot on the emergence of private
commercial fractional reserve banking
with the emergence of the Bank of
England in 1694 what are any of your
work that touches on that particular
phenomenon yes absolutely so in the wake
of the 2007-2008 banking meltdown there
sprung up a very good literature from in
ciders to outsiders about how how to
understand bank runs leveraged
instruments fractional reserve lending
and the instabilities in those systems
and that took us all the way back to
Badgett and the rise of fractional
reserve banking in london and the
fragility against bank runs that that
brought with it and then the emergence
of lender insurance as the stabilization
institution against bank runs and the
only paper martin and i ever wrote that
was accepted for publication without a
terrible fight was our paper on
self-fulfilling prophecies and bank runs
and that was because i could make a
simple statistical model of how you can
enter a banking contract for fractional
reserves believing that the payoff is
better than you can get by staying out
of that market and yet once you're in
there you can be subject to the
instability of a bank run if people wind
up essentially escaping from the basin
of Attraction of trust now the
interesting thing is I always wanted to
follow that up with a model of the
mortgage-backed securities and the the
collateralized loans the repo markets
that were the source of instability that
set off the 2007-2008 problem absolutely
let me insert here just for the audience
you know I spent a lot of time
researching this in the 2008 to 2012
range and I found one book that did the
best job called slapped by the invisible
hand yes by Gary Gorton at Yale I
believe his forensics is the correct one
if there's a call out to folks that
might want to do their own reading in
this Gary Gorton and also Michael
Woodford those two were two we read
heavily and in the Journal of economic
literature they have some excellent
articles some of which were collected in
Gary's book so yeah super sources on
both of those so if you look at the way
markets for repurchase agreements work
it's clear that if the securities behind
them are priced using mark-to-market
methods that system is inherently
unstable
and it's it's almost like a classical
electrical engineering design of
amplifiers you could write it down and
ask when the poles go outside the unit
circle I always wanted to do that never
got around to it because it would be a
perfect application of Martin's
strategic market game formulation but
after Gary and Michael had written I
didn't feel like there were any new
problems left for us to solve so it was
never a priority to do but the
interesting thing you can ask is if
everybody knows it's unstable why did
they go into it or if they know that
it's unstable because mark-to-market
intrinsically replaces the diversity
that is the assumption for
representative agents and stabilizing
the economy with a sort of a mechanized
everybody steps on the same foot at the
same time why would they do that well
they do it because it gives you legal
defensibility you can claim you're using
best practices when you get sued so this
was one of Martin's favorite things when
you look at something pathological in
the economy look for where it comes from
the law as its origin and so the
interesting question about all of this
is how does the legal system create
homogenize ation in people's actions by
replacing their intrinsic diversity with
algorithmic homogeneity and then how do
these institutions like mark-to-market
interact with the adoption of repurchase
agreements on very fast turnover markets
to create a system that has these
overnight instabilities a huge scale
yeah not only the first-order effect but
I thought what Gorton was particularly
brilliant at was he looked at the
phenomena of rehypothecation of
collateral in the repo market which was
a very peculiar thing but turned I
believe and I think Gorton does too was
the actual spring that imploded and
caused what was a big economic error
about a trillion dollars worth of bad
mortgages into a near collapse of
monetary system which is where a bank
let's use Bear Stearns as an example
they were the one of the biggest players
in a repo market and they get a pile of
collateralized mortgage obligations in
the form of a security as collateral for
their repo they are allowed under US law
to take 40% of that Andry lend it to
somebody else that person can do 40% etc
in London it's a hundred percent so you
can essentially have a
infinite expansion of the near money
supply through this overnight
rehypothecation of collateral phenomenon
and when Lehman went down and panic
ensued
everybody refused to take we hypothesize
collateral and this gigantic six
trillion dollar pseudo money near money
phenomenon imploded down to about five
hundred and fifty billions so more than
90 percent of it disappeared in two
weeks and that was the shock wave that
almost brought the house down yeah this
is wonderful it brings up two other
people that I think we want to call out
in this conversation one is John Jana
Capello's who was interested in haircut
revaluation but your real point is that
the magnitude of the bad death was
absorbable but the fact that people
didn't know where it was was what pulled
down the system and for this there's a
wonderful book Hyman Minsky stabilising
an unstable economy and I can use your
podcast to get a term out in circulation
that I never got to use in a paper I
want to call that argument Minsky's
ratchet which is that during stable
times when you need regulation you can't
muster the political will to get
regulation in the necessary forms and so
the quality of credit degrades and
degrades through innovations like
rehypothecation then when things go bad
there's only one actor who can act on
the necessary scale and on the necessary
short time frame and that's the central
bank and the government and there's no
government that will choose not to act
unless it chooses to collapse its own
economic system so it almost doesn't
matter who's in power if you have anyone
who's not willing to implode the country
that actor is gonna bail the system out
everybody's gonna howl about it but the
horse is out of the gate the time when
you needed regulation is passed
you can put the regulation on ex-post
but there's too much entropy in the
system that money has been dispersed
there's too much information gone and
you can't recover it which is what we
saw in the mortgage-backed securities
case
and so there's a meta question here how
do we overcome Minsky's ratchet how do
we maintain political and legal
vigilance so that it's active during the
times when it's needed but people are
comfortable and they're not good at
assessing the fragility in the system
and ideas well this is what the systemic
risk people ought to have good ideas in
I have not done original work in this
area
apart from sort of thinking that this is
the problem so no I I can't offer much
that I think has substance in this too
bad that would have been fun now let's
talk a little bit about money versus its
substitutes various near monies did you
guys look into that any yes a lot one of
Martin's ideas was that money is only
made effective when it is surrounded by
suitable forms of credit that give the
degrees of flexibility that the central
money system can't and he was always
interested in things like the
monetization of personal credit concepts
like the real bills doctrine that
supported much of mercantil English
traffic what what did we call it when
England was the Merchant Marine of the
world mercantile capitalism I guess yep
sounds reasonable
yeah so he was interested in how you can
take things like promissory notes that
are generated in a local distributed
fashion and which are therefore
sensitive to local conditions and then
what the bank wants is a credit
evaluation feature that will allow it to
pick and choose among these distributed
instruments monetizing them stabilizing
them by trading them for things like
government money or gold
thus leveraging their flexibility but
then giving them the stability to
function as money's on a much larger
scale the reason Martin was interested
in this is that it highlights the need
for trusts and institutions as the
foundation of money because when you
have these near monies or monetized
credits you can have a many fold
expansion of the volume of trade that's
supported but exactly as you say when
rehypothecation came to not be trusted
you can have the collapse of all of
these near monies down to sort of the
core of trusted money which can be a
small fraction
of what the trade-in process had been
assuming very true when it worked it
worked when it doesn't it doesn't that
seems to be the nature of monetary
systems right and for those who are
interested in some of this I have an
hour-and-a-half video called dividend
money might check it out on YouTube this
has been very interesting on before we
go though on money of course I have to
ask you what are your thoughts about the
new alternative currencies the crypto
currencies etc can they possibly escape
their little miniature basins of
attraction and become significant not in
the trivializing way that their
proponents hope there's a kind of a
simplified view of the world that one
sees a lot in engineering which comes
from knowing one system very well and
imagining that that's a surrogate for
the world instead of just one little
component in a world that remains
complex the cryptocurrencies fill a role
in distributed authentication that's
very hard to fill because the problem is
always who will guard the Guardians what
happens when every institution that
provides trust is not ultimately
trustworthy but our money is a
complicated system it requires
low-friction
the crypto currencies have the feature
of limited availability scarcity which
secures the stability value of money but
they don't have the institutional
surroundings that make money predictable
you know gold is incompressible and if
you have a gold only economy every shock
in that economy every speculation every
surprise propagates through the entire
economy so you really don't want your
retirement savings in Bitcoin if you're
relatively old today and we will be
brought back to these classic questions
of how one creates a stable society and
a stable set of laws and monetary
institutions and I think what we will
want is to embed the crypto currencies
within that larger conversation about
how they can contribute to the stability
of institutions and then benefit from it
instead of envisioning them as a
replacement for it all and if nothing
else I mean look at the energy footprint
of cryptocurrencies right now which is
completely irresponsible you're trying
to be a speculative Sarah
for the entire rest of the world instead
of using themselves as a window to
better understand the world and know how
to make it more robust that's the kind
of naive mistake that we see being made
with everything when it's first
introduced yeah I agree a hundred
percent I own zero Bitcoin and I'm happy
to be there my friend Ben Gert Sol likes
to joke that bitcoin is nothing but a
way to accelerate the heat death of the
universe right basically stupid
computing burning up some non-trivial
amount of all the electricity on earth
so with that let's exit money and
finance some really interesting insights
let's move on to our next topic which is
language its origins and evolution talk
a little bit about how you got
interested in that idea and sort of the
big picture what you're thinking is
there yes the languages have always been
a joy they're a thing that we're all
embedded in we have an enormous amount
of tacit knowledge both as speakers of
our own language and as participants in
whatever languages surround us and
anybody who's a young kid and encounters
some foreign languages for the first
time will have experienced this wonder
that things in a foreign language
suddenly make sense of things in your
own language that you never understood
before
so you know if you grow up as a speaker
of English you should be perplexed and
appalled that it's even a pronounceable
language because it's rules are so
Byzantine but then if you encounter
Italian which is a logical language
suddenly you realize that half of
English is logical but it's the logic of
Latin and then the other half you can
recognize as logical but it's the logic
of German and in English starts to
become comprehensible so when we went to
SFI and I encountered a group that was
seriously working on reconstructing the
history of all of the world's languages
as a platform from which to understand
language as a phenomenon I thought okay
this is a once-in-a-lifetime opportunity
can't pass this up
but the thing that's fascinating is that
linguistics is an excessively
conservative field and they resisted
using modern probability methods much
longer than they should have they're
starting to do it now but it's four
decades later than it should have been
so at SFI the linguist wanted to engage
the biologists
who had been using probability methods
for genomics for some decades but that
was often a frustrating exchange and it
was frustrating because of human
difficulty the biologists were too
arrogant thinking they had solved
problems and too uninterested in
learning the depth of what linguists
knew about the structure of language
that's different from the structure of
genome dynamics and the linguists were
too stuck in the mud to try to use a
polite term to be willing to put in the
hard work of being students of
probability methods and really taking
them on in their modern form and I
remember witnessing these exchanges and
thinking this is insane if either side
of this would exercise little humility
and really become a student of the other
side we could open up this whole study
so that of course turned out to be a lot
harder to do than to complain about and
it took us seven years of work to get
the manpower to actually do a very
simple version of this problem by the
time we got it done and got it published
the rest of the world was already
starting to do this at a good level but
this system is still really gold on the
ground for whoever wants to start to
work in this area because we know so
much about probability methods and we
know so much about the structure of
language but to really work from whole
cloth and make probabilistic models of
the intrinsic dynamics of language use
and language change that is yet to be
done and some young generation with time
that wants to pick this up can really
create a new field
you mentioned language change I know
that was a big interest of the SFI group
working around language what insights
did you get about how languages evolved
and change it presents I'm going to
answer you as a physicist because I love
the phenomena in themselves in their
diversity but I also like the patterns
that we see they unify the phenomena and
the interesting thing is that with
genome change we can get a long way by
looking at changes that are not context
dependent so you can look at the flips
of individual bases and how they create
your properties and organisms or how
they don't create new properties so they
can stay around for long
time is a signature of population splits
language only functions because its
components are a system there's no magic
and the fact that I begin the word
language with Allah sound except that
the sound law is used in all the other
words in English where law is used and
that's what gives it its meaning it's
contrast against the other things that
are different sounds so if the sound law
is gonna change to something else it's
gonna have to do it in all of the places
where it appears in English at the same
time and it's gonna have to change for
all the speakers of English at the same
time that makes the modeling of language
change a very different problem than the
modeling of genome change in many
respects the sort of the joint change of
the system with the tokens that carry
the properties of the system and that's
rich
because context discovery remains a hard
problem it's one of the interesting
problems in deep learning I would love
to see the deep learning community which
has been so data centric start to take
more of an interest in grammar discovery
syntax discovery and things like that to
which they have been resistant so far
because I think we will learn more about
the nature of grammar when we start to
ask deep learning systems to unpack what
they know about language like the zero
shot translation so that they can start
to discover things about grammar and
syntax that we have not yet observed
makes sense because it is reasonably
close right unfortunately it's not the
way that most deep learning people are
thinking though there are beginning to
be some people who are willing to think
about what's inside the black box and
how to interpret the black box and
something closer to symbolic terms
because if there's anything that
symbolic its language for sure right
well it's a collaboration
I would like to entice somebody in
because we know that to have deep
learners unpack their knowledge and
present it to us an understandable form
is certainly a thing the deep learning
community is interested in and language
would be a great place to work because
we have the results on zero shot so we
know we have some working black boxes
and we have a template for the kinds of
things to look for because however
incomplete it may be
understanding of grammar and typology
syntax morphology all these components
is very rich and it's it's a good type
of logical space that's a collaboration
that we should be pursuing and I hope
somebody is successful in sort of
grabbing the interest of the people who
are very much in demand on both sides of
this problem very very true one person I
know working on Salamis Vectis very
interesting guy who's looking at doing
what he calls grammar induction so the
theory is you take a big enough corpus
of language in the wild and actually
induce the grammar in a mechanical way
he's not all the way there yet but he's
making some progress so he's a person to
keep an eye on in that space we
shouldn't reinvigorate that conversation
and do a workshop at SFI on that
question I'll tell you what I'll
introduce you to Lennis and see if you
guys kind of resonate enough in your
approaches to maybe you can be the dyad
that then turns into a workshop I'm
happy to do the organizational stuff a
testify yeah terrific let's put that
together and keep tunneling in the loop
too because I know he continues to want
to do this ah that would be great let me
ask you and a little bit less scientific
questions but more kind of pop questions
about language and its origins is do you
have a view or do you have any reason to
have a view about when something like
our full language came into existence I
mean there's some theories that say hey
we were speaking something pretty close
to Chomsky in languages 300 thousand
years ago and then other people say nah
it was only 40,000 years ago and some
people even say that it was only 10,000
years ago do you have a dog in that
fight no I'm the tourist of those
opinions kind of the same way that you
are
I read the arguments given for each of
them but I don't have anything to add
that would give me a unique take if you
had to pick one what would be your best
guess I would go in the hundred thousand
year ballpark in the sense that that
seems to be when we get the modern form
of Y chromosome and the already in place
modern form of the mitochondrion there
may be later changes in human genome
that we don't easily see but I don't see
what would have changed overall brain
development
much later than that the question of
what is the cause of cultural modernity
the apparent horizon at 40,000 years
remains interesting and compelling I
agree here's my contribution to this
discussion as I say it has to be more
than 65 thousand years ago and here's
why the Out of Africa migration that was
the one from which almost all non
African people are descended happened
about 65 thousand years ago and there's
almost no genetic backflow to Africa for
a very long time and yet chomskyan
language exists in both Africa and
outside Africa therefore the capability
to have full language had to have
existed sixty five thousand years ago
yeah that sounds right to me I think
that seems to be a pretty clean way to
look at anything else you want to say
about language before we move on to
sustainability know nothing to know
though okay that's cool now this is
something that I don't know to what
degree you've made an academic study of
it but you and I have talked about it in
fact I recall when you invited Joel
Salatin Joel Salatin who as it turns out
is my neighbor and we now know real well
Eric invited Joel Salatin to talk at an
SFI event and then you and I talked
quite a bit about that before and after
and you clearly have a lot of thoughts
about the fact one that we're if
we don't change our ways and two at
least some thoughts on what that might
mean so why don't you give us our
thoughts on where we're at with respect
to ecosystem sustainability and what are
some of the roads we need to think about
going down if we're gonna actually get
there yeah the way I entered this
conversation was through a collaboration
of Agriculture and medicine people of
all kinds that they really are citizens
in that some of them are researchers
some of them are practitioners some are
policy people there are working farmers
and doctors from all different contexts
and the collaboration was formed around
the idea that we know how to do better
than we actually do in practice what
would a better form for the world look
like and where our knowledge is
insufficient where should our
investigative efforts most go and so
these were participants like West
Jackson who founded the land Institute
to create the
cept of perennial polyculture but also
people interested in soil microbial
ecology as the sort of foundation of
farming before you worry about what you
put in the soil diversified cropping
systems plant animal mutualisms and how
they affect the long-term viability of
soils and terrains and then how this
integrates back into the sort of
large-scale geological processes of
continental weathering things that Sir
Albert Howard was worried about in what
he called the law of return so what are
the natural roles of forests as miners
of trace metals and then grasslands as
the inheritors of what forest mine with
their deep roots and how these biota on
the whole contribute to the sort of
mountain to coast process of continental
weathering what's the big picture so
I've inherited a lot of that
conversation the luminaries in it were
people like West Jackson Wendell burry
the question I asked Joel when he came
to SFI was how do our solutions on the
small scale scale to a world that is now
big and interconnected and there are
people like Wendell who don't like that
they don't like the idea of anything on
a big scale because their argument which
has a lot of weight is that the problems
were stuck on are complex and the only
way you solve complex problems is by
having a very deep local understanding
that certainly is true and I think it's
profound but at the same time a
watershed or a continent or a large
Society are interconnected entities and
so we can't escape the fact that we
influence each other we have to
understand on the small scale but we
have to coordinate on the large scale
and a place where I don't think anybody
has good solutions is how do we leverage
that small scale complex understanding
how do we feedback to really support it
how do we keep local farming on the land
at a sophisticated level which it's not
right now
by having it supports for it come from
the big system but then how do we keep
the big system constrained by feeding
from and using all of that locally
acquired knowledge that's the big system
problem and there are lots there lot
some little movements that are trying to
do this and you know great support them
in any way we can I don't see them in
pinching on the big structures that have
lock in on the industrial farming system
and on the terrible waste and
inefficiency that the demographics of
our society has overall and that
structural change has to happen or we're
really in trouble
yeah the way I sometimes phrase it is
probably the solutions are local but the
system has to close globally right
either we run into the wall at 120 miles
an hour and cook the planet and destroy
our soils or we don't and unfortunately
we have a real bad collective action
problem here we have to have behaviors
locally that are correct but yet they
have to add up and close algebraically
arithmetic alii even at a global level a
real conundrum this is right this goes
back to where we open the conversation
about herb Simon and systems thinking
and Creek in the central dogma so in
order to have hierarchical structure you
need control systems and that means that
the controller has to be able to make
the controlled do what it would not do
on its own otherwise you don't need a
controller but that opens the problem
that the controller is not immediately
subject to feedbacks it can be wrong and
it can give wrong instructions maybe for
a long time so how do we leverage the
benefits of having control systems but
keep them responsive enough that when
they're giving the wrong instructions
they can't continue to do it long enough
to crash the system and we see that in
every level we see it in the nature of
business and the theory of the firm we
see it in the economy we see it in the
problems of sustainability of social
order we see it in the question of what
is democracy and what is required what
is the aspiration of democracy what form
would fulfill it and what do we need to
maintain it which is sort of a problem
of major urgency around the world right
now so I think there's a meta question
at the system's level what is the common
thing that we are failing to understand
in all of these questions and how can we
how can we do better in bringing ideas
to that problem yeah it strikes me that
it's how do we create hierarchical or at
least emergent entities that have
multiple levels it may not be formally
higher
charcoal that nonetheless cohere
together in real time and we have an
example of that in the human body right
we have billions of autonomous agents
called ourselves right that we're at
least originally free-floating single
cells way back yonder and evolutionary
time and yet we have this astounding
homeostasis binds them all together in
exchange of gases both bad gas out good
gas in nutrients and toxins in this
astounding modulated by a hierarchical
system and it seems to me that our world
system needs to learn from that and be
able to hold itself together coherently
in approximately real time despite
operating on multi scale simultaneously
yes yeah you know transition from single
cells to multi cells who it went through
and what innovations were needed is a
topic that a lot of people are looking
at these days and it's a wonderful area
it'll be interesting to see what we
learn about the nature of regulation
from trying to understand that better
yeah unfortunately we don't have a lot
of time it'll have time for it probably
for the answer to come from that kind of
basic science seems to me that if we
don't reform our ways advanced modern
society is gonna run into the wall
probably no later than 2100 so we've got
to essentially innovate at higher levels
of abstraction I'm afraid rather than
wait for answers from lower-level
research yeah that seems right to me too
have you given any thought at all to
what kind of signalling modalities what
kind of control systems what kind of
governance might be appropriate in this
new world let's call it we gotta get it
in place by 2050 kind of timeframe
there's a book I think by Paul Hawken
called Blessed unrest and he has a
database behind it or did a few years
ago which is an attempt to collect all
of the civil society organizations that
he could learn about and put them in a
place where they can find each other
we need a better theory of governance we
can see governance being hollowed out by
the sort of takeover of concentrated
interests that are coming from private
organizations at this time so government
has a separate
representation and organization in the
society away from business or wealthy
individuals or land that is being
weakened and that needs to be brought
back but presumably civil society is the
other pillar which is the smaller and
more disaggregated cousin to government
and I feel like the right conversation
is going back to the conversation from
Adam Smith's time but in the
institutional world of today rather than
the one that he lived in
we have firms we have markets we have
wealth concentrating mechanisms and we
have private ownership we for good or
for ill are going to have massive
information gathering and control
mechanisms we have civil society and we
have government what is the most stable
ecosystem of those components that we
can foresee and try to design that's the
way I would put the sort of big picture
question yeah actually I'm putting a lot
of my efforts right now what I call the
mezzo scale it used to be that a lot of
what made our lives both doable and
pleasant was from either the family or
the local face-to-face community but
over the last two hundred years most of
that has been ceded to either the
governments or the markets and it seems
to me we need to find a way to
revitalize a mezzo scale on the order of
hundreds and a few thousand people some
people call that civil society but it
may actually have more structure to it
than unstructured civil society any
thoughts on whether that's a useful
scale to be prospecting on my thoughts
are that I agree with your sensibility
but I also think this is where you ought
to have a good China Scholar in place
because if I understand correctly some
of the things that are guiding Chinese
governance right now are kind of a
distrust in the controllability of that
meso scale which is why they're trying
to weaken that and replace it with
centralized control it would be really
interesting to have somebody who's
informed and sophisticated in where that
line of thought comes from on this
conversation and say why do they
distrust it to what extent do they
mistrust it why do they think they can
live without it if that's what they
think what do they think can replace it
and sort of what's the merit of our
from the evidence we have about what
problems can be solved by institutions
at each of these scales I would be
really interested to listen to informed
people have that conversation do you
have any pointers to people who are
thinking in this space well there was a
frontline documentary on AI in the
context of Chinese governance today we
could look to people on there and we
could start in that as a network of
exploration with some of the people who
appeared in that show either they
themselves or people they would
recommend that's where I would start
because I'm kind of new to this all
right that's great I'm gonna go mine
that I'll let you know what I find out
well we're getting close to the end of
our time here this has been as I knew it
would an unbelievably deep and
interesting set of conversations about a
wider range of topics and one could ever
imagine any one person having in their
head but before we go could you tell us
what you're working on now and what you
might be working on yeah the work
continues to be sort of at the interface
of organized geochemistry and the deep
origins of biology I'm getting more into
the domain of folding and the origin of
biopolymers than I used to because I
have collaborators at Georgia Tech or
some of the world experts in that
problem we are looking again at the
genetic code and that's where some my
earlier comments when that came from but
I should say that there's a a meta
question that to me is the interesting
question that reps many of these others
together we often think about biology in
terms of its extraordinary capacity to
carry information and that capacity only
exists because biology creates big
combinatorial state spaces that in
physics terms we would say are
relatively flat so there can be big
genomes where any sequence is really
available the substrate of the material
gene doesn't fight you from making one
sequence versus another and that means
that relatively weak forces like
selection at the individual level can
cause you to migrate around in that
genome space and there is a similar
story to be told for protein catalysts
where you can kind of make any sequence
and you can fold lots of them and you
can catalyze with lots of them but I
think if you're a physicist and you know
how heterogeneous chemistry is you would
say that these large combatant
spaces that are physically neutral are
not typical in a chemical system the
typical thing in the chemical system is
for configurational heterogeneity to be
so big that it just wipes out any kind
of combinatorial flatness so if we want
to understand why biospheres are
possible we need to understand where
there are sort of linchpin steps they're
not combinatorial in themselves they're
often small chemical problems but they
create narrow bottlenecks anneal those
bottlenecks reject enough of the
configuration entropy of the problem
that the stuff that gets through the
bottleneck then becomes a combinatorial
e large and flat space that's capable of
carrying information so that was
probably a little bit technically higher
level than you want for your podcast but
the the sort of soundbite compression of
it is that we want to understand when
and how systems that are capable of
carrying a lot of information become
available without being buried in the
heterogeneity of the physical material
they're made of and I think that's a
question where physics and biology can
productively interface Wow alright that
is wonderful I want to thank you very
much for being on here I think our
audience will have learned a heck of a
lot if they make it here to the end it's
a pleasure to be here and it's great to
be in contact with you on going
[Music]
production services and audio editing by
jerod Jane's consulting music by Tom
Muller at modern space